Guide to the Saundra Sturdevant Photography Archive M2005
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Saundra Sturdevant Photography Archive
1981-2002
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Sturdevant, Saundra Pollock
Lanza, Fabio
M2005
24 Linear Feet (8 RSBs, 2 MBs, 13 flat boxes)
Saundra Sturdevant was photojournalist specializing in women's labor issues. The collection contains many prints, slides and negatives, as well as material for her book “Let the Good Times Roll: Prostitution and the U.S. Military in Asia.”
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Fabio Lanza, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy
Biographical / Historical
Saundra Pollack Sturdevant (d. 2013) was an Asian scholar, photojournalist, and activist specializing in women's labor issues. Sturdevant grew up rural Missouri, earned her PhD in modern Chinese history at the University of Chicago, and attended UC Berkeley for her post-doc, later teaching there. In the 1980s, she largely left academia for photography after she began taking pictures in Beijing. For much of her career, Sturdevant focused on relations between overseas servicemen and the local "comfort" industry, particularly in Asia. She founded the Migrant Photography Project in California, teaching photography and self-documentation to women farmworkers. She also worked in India, Mexico and Hawaii, and was active in the Quakers’ American Friend Service Committee.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains prints, slides and negatives, as well as material related to her 1992 book coauthored with Brenda Stoltzfus "Let the Good Times Roll: Prostitution and the U.S. Military in Asia" (abbreviated as LGTR in the listing), as well as the unpublished "HER-EYES: The Creation of Olongapo as a Military Rest and Recreation Center."
The collection has been minimally processed, and all folder titles are transcribed from her original files, where present.
Documentary photography; Sturdevant, Saundra Pollock; Lanza, Fabio
- Pablo Espinoza: Historical Archive in Progress, 2001-01 (Box 1, Folders 1-4)
- Hainan Slides, 1988 (Box 1, Folders 5-8)
- Philippines Slides (Box 2)
- Okinawa, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folders 1-2)
- Her Eyes: The Creation of Olongapo as a Military Rest and Recreation Center (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Her Eyes Interviews, 1999-02 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Why are there… (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Her Eyes - General (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Doc. Film (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Her Eyes Interviews, 1999-02 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Her Eyes Interviews, 1999-02 (Box 4, Folders 1-2)
- Interviews Pts.1-2, 1999 (Box 4, Folders 3-4)
- Draft Chapters (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Seigal Doc (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Her Eyes-Research to do (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Her Eyes Photo Release (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Her Eyes (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Interviews #1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Philippines Interviews BUKLOD Staff (Box 4, Folder 11)
- BUKLOD, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Interviews (Box 4, Folders 13-15)
- Her Eyes (Box 5, Folders 1-4)
- Nic. B/W Prints, 1984 (Box 5, Folders 5-7)
- China, 1987-1989 (Box 6, Folders 1-2)
- China Minbei (Box 6, Folders 3-4)
- Her Eyes Philippines Portraits, Copy Negs., 1999 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- CA Agiu, 1998-2005 (Box 6, Folders 6-8)
- India (Box 6, Folders 9-10)
- Korea Slides, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folders 1-3)
- Japan (1986) Hong Kong (1988), 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Taiwai Hong Kong Slides, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folders 5-8)
- Pussycat III Videos from LGTR (Box 7, Folders 9-10)
- LGTR Video LGTR Slide Show Philippines Slide Show (Box 8, Folders 1-3)
- LGTR Korea (Box 8, Folders 4-6)
- Okinawa Slides (Box 8, Folders 7-9)
- LGTR Okinawa (Box 9, Folders 1-3)
- Okinawa Slides 2 (Box 9, Folders 4-6)
- LGTR Philippines (Box 9, Folders 7-10)
- Vietnam (Box 9, Folder 11)
- LGTR Book Print Images (Box 10, Folders 1-11)
- Copy Negatives LGTR (Box 11, Folders 1-7)
- China B/W Prints (Box 11, Folders 8-11)
- China B/W Prints (Box 12, Folders 1-6)
- 1984 - SF - Anti Intervention Demo 1984, 1990 SF Mime Troop 1991 - 19 Jan Anti Gulf War - SF 1991 - Jan., 1984-1991 (Box 12, Folders 7-9)
- California Agriculture Negatives, 1993-1999 (Box 12, Folders 10-11)
- California Dairy, 1999-2002 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Copy Negs. India, California (Box 12, Folders 13-14)
- China B/W Prints (Box 13, Folders 1-2)
- Philippines Slides (Box 14, Folders 1-8)
- India Field #2 CD (Box 15, Object 1)
- India Recycle, Domestic CD (Box 15, Object 2)
- India Sewer Pipes Laundry CD (Box 15, Object 3)
- India Charcoal CD (Box 15, Object 4)
- India Rock Work Textile CD (Box 15, Object 5)
- Widelux #1-2 (Box 15, Object 6-7)
- India Aqui Labor - India digital some for work CD (Box 15, Object 8)
- Dairy digital copy Burned 5 CDs, 2005-01 (Box 15, Object 9)
- Image Pablo Espinosa UFW CD (Box 15, Object 10)
- Indie PSD Portfolio 4 CDs (Box 15, Object 11)
- Pussycat III Sturdevant Stoltzfus CD (Box 15, Object 12)
- Women's Agricultural Labor Project - California 20 digital images S. Sturdevant CD (Box 15, Object 13)
- Dairy + Pesticides June CD, 2007-11 (Box 15, Object 14)
- Saundra Sturdevant Final Web Portfolios 060314 - CA - India 4 CDs, 2006 (Box 15, Object 15)
- Web - Oaxaca - to David External (11 Photos) CD, 2008-11-04 (Box 15, Object 16)
- ICA Psd - 2 CDs BU -ICD of 3 PSD files CD (Box 15, Object 17)
- India final tifs, India Web Materials & India Web Portfolio CD, 2006 (Box 16, Object 1)
- CA Row Scans 1 of 2 2008 CD and Saundra Sturdevant 2006 CA final tifs (Box 16, Object 2)
- Untitled Folders (Box 17, Folders 1-5)
- Miscellaneous Photograph (Box 18, Folder 1)
- F11 18s 1 1/2 Dindoors BF8 / 8s Photographs (Box 18, Folder 2)
- F11 13s 2F D Shad of hut B 13s Ltonid B 13s R curve down 13s Top & L corner (Box 18, Folder 3)
- F8 10s 2F D ground & person B5=Ls 1 Sky (Box 18, Folder 4)
- F16 3F 20s Dcoro B Balt RL15sBott 6ft5s 10sSky (Box 18, Folder 5)
- 516 24s 3F D B Bott & L 24s (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Untitled Folders (Box 19, Folders 1-2)
- Photographs by Saundra Sturdevant (Box 19, Folders 3-6)
- Untitled Folders (Box 20, Folders 1-7)
- Untitled Folders (Box 21, Folders 1-7)
- Untitled Folders (Box 22, Folders 1-6)
- Untitled Folders (Box 23, Folders 1-6)
- Untitled Folders (Box 24, Folders 1-7)
- Untitled Folders (Box 25, Folders 1-6)
- Untitled Folders (Box 26, Folders 1-18)
- Untitled Folders (Box 27, Folders 1-22)
- Untitled Folders (Box 28, Folders 1-9)
- Untitled Folders (Box 29, Folders 1-16)